As a particle physicist, I study the elementary particles
كعالمة فيزياء مختصة بالجسيمات، أدرس الجسيمات الأولية
and how they interact on the most fundamental level.
وكيف تتفاعل مع بعضها البعض في المستوى الأساسي.
For most of my research career, I've been using accelerators,
في خلال معظم حياتي المهنية قمت باستخدام مسارعات الجسيمات ،
such as the electron accelerator at Stanford University, just up the road,
مثل مسارع الإلكترون في جامعة ستانفورد ، الواقع في الطريق الرئيسي ،
to study things on the smallest scale.
لدراسة الأشياء على مقياس مصغر.
But more recently, I've been turning my attention
ولكن مؤخرا ، أصبحت أوجه تركيزي
to the universe on the largest scale.
على الكون على مقياس أكبر.
Because, as I'll explain to you,
لأنه ، كما سأشرح لكم ،
the questions on the smallest and the largest scale are actually very connected.
الغموض حول الأشياء المتناهية الصغر والأحجام الكبيرة في الحقيقة مترابطان جدا.
So I'm going to tell you about our twenty-first-century view of the universe,
لذلك سأخبركم عن تصورنا للكون في القرن الحادي والعشرين ،
what it's made of and what the big questions in the physical sciences are --
مما يتكون الكون وماهي الإجابات التي نبحث عنها في علم الفيزياء --
at least some of the big questions.
على الأقل البعض من الإجابات المهمة التي نبحث عنها.
So, recently, we have realized
ومؤخرا جدا ، أدركنا أن
that the ordinary matter in the universe --
المادة الطبيعية في الكون --
and by ordinary matter, I mean you, me,
وعندما أقول المادة الطبيعية أعني أنتم ، حسنا ، أنا
the planets, the stars, the galaxies --
الكواكب ، النجوم ، المجرات --
the ordinary matter makes up only a few percent
المادة الطبيعية تكون فقط نسبة بسيطة
of the content of the universe.
من المادة المكونة للكون.
Almost a quarter, or approximately a quarter
و ربع المادة المكونة للكون ، أو تقريبا ربع
of the matter in the universe, is stuff that's invisible.
المادة الكونية ، هي أشياء غير مرئية.
By invisible, I mean it doesn't absorb in the electromagnetic spectrum.
وعندما أقول غير مرئية أعني أنها لا تمتص موجات الطيف الكهرومغناطيسي.
It doesn't emit in the electromagnetic spectrum. It doesn't reflect.
ولا تبعث الطيف الكهرومغناطيسي ولا تعكسه.
It doesn't interact with the electromagnetic spectrum,
بل إنها لا تتفاعل مع موجات الطيف الكهرومغناطيسي ،
which is what we use to detect things.
وهو ما نستخدمه للتعرف على الأجسام الكونية.
It doesn't interact at all. So how do we know it's there?
لا تتفاعل معه مطلقا. إذن كيف علمنا بوجودها ؟
We know it's there by its gravitational effects.
نحن نعلم بوجودها بسبب تأثير جاذبيتها.
In fact, this dark matter dominates
في الحقيقة ، المادة المظلمة تسيطر على
the gravitational effects in the universe on a large scale,
تأثير الجاذبية في الكون كله على مقياس أكبر ،
and I'll be telling you about the evidence for that.
وسأخبركم عن أدلة على ذلك.
What about the rest of the pie?
ولكن ماذا عن تكملة الرسمة ؟
The rest of the pie is a very mysterious substance called dark energy.
تكملة الرسمة عبارة عن شيء غامض جدا يسمى الطاقة المظلمة.
More about that later, OK.
سنتحدث عنه لاحقا ، حسنا.
So for now, let's turn to the evidence for dark matter.
اذا الان ، لنتحدث عن الأدلة على وجود المادة المظلمة.
In these galaxies, especially in a spiral galaxy like this,
في هذه المجرات ، خاصة في مجرة حلزونية مثل هذه ،
most of the mass of the stars is concentrated in the middle of the galaxy.
فإن أغلب الكتلة للنجوم مركزة في وسط المجرة.
This huge mass of all these stars keeps stars in circular orbits in the galaxy.
وهذا الكم الهائل من الكتلة لكل هذه النجوم يبقي النجوم في مدار دائري في المجرة.
So we have these stars going around in circles like this.
لذلك فإن هذه النجوم تدور في دائرة بهذا الشكل.
As you can imagine, even if you know physics, this should be intuitive, OK --
وكما نتخيل ، و لو أنكم درستم الفيزياء -- فإن هذا يجب أن يكون بدهيا ، حسنا --
that stars that are closer to the mass in the middle will be rotating at a higher speed
أن النجوم التي قريبة من مركز الكتلة ستدور بسرعة أكبر
than those that are further out here, OK.
من النجوم التي هي أبعد في هذه المنطقة ، حسنا.
So what you would expect is that if you measured the orbital speed of the stars,
لذلك من الطبيعي أن نفترض أننا لو قمنا بقياس السرعة المدارية للنجوم ،
that they should be slower on the edges than on the inside.
أنها ستكون أبطء في الأطراف من التي في الداخل.
In other words, if we measured speed as a function of distance --
وبمعنى اخر ، إذا قمنا بقياس السرعة كمعادلة بمتغير المسافة --
this is the only time I'm going to show a graph, OK --
هذه هي المرة الوحيدة التي سأعرض فيها رسم بياني ، حسنا --
we would expect that it goes down as the distance increases
سنتوقع أن السرعة ستقل كلما ازدادت المسافة
from the center of the galaxy.
من مركز المجرة.
When those measurements are made,
وعندما أخذت هذه القياسات ،
instead what we find is that the speed is basically constant,
بدلا من ذلك وجدنا أن السرعة ثابتة ،
as a function of distance.
مع تغير المسافة.
If it's constant, that means that the stars out here
وإذا كانت السرعة ثابتة ، هذا يعني أن النجوم هنا
are feeling the gravitational effects of matter that we do not see.
تتأثر بتأثير جاذبية لمادة لا نستطيع رؤيتها.
In fact, this galaxy and every other galaxy
في الحقيقة ، فإن هذه المجرة وكل المجرات الأخرى
appears to be embedded in a cloud of this invisible dark matter.
تبدوا وكأنها محاطة بسحابة من هذه المادة المظلمة.
And this cloud of matter is much more spherical than the galaxy themselves,
وهذه السحابة من المادة أكثر كروية من المجرات نفسها
and it extends over a much wider range than the galaxy.
وتتمدد حول نطاق أكبر بكثير من المجرة
So we see the galaxy and fixate on that, but it's actually a cloud of dark matter
نحن نرى المجرة لذا نركز فيها ، بينما أنها في سحابة ضخمة من المادة المظلمة
that's dominating the structure and the dynamics of this galaxy.
وهو ما يسيطر على بنية المجرة وحركتها.
Galaxies themselves are not strewn randomly in space;
بل إن المجرات لا تنتشر في الفضاء عشوائيا ؛
they tend to cluster.
ولكن تتجه إلى التجمع.
And this is an example of a very, actually, famous cluster, the Coma cluster.
وهذا مثال على تجمع مشهور جدا للمجرات يدعى : تجمع كوما ( Coma )
And there are thousands of galaxies in this cluster.
وهناك الالاف من المجرات في هذا التجمع.
They're the white, fuzzy, elliptical things here.
إنها عبارة عن تجمع بيضوي غامض أبيض اللون.
So these galaxy clusters -- we take a snapshot now,
وهذه التجمعات للمجرات -- إذا أخذنا صورة لها في هذه اللحظة ،
we take a snapshot in a decade, it'll look identical.
وأخذنا صورة لها بعد عشر سنوات -- ستبدوا متطابقة.
But these galaxies are actually moving at extremely high speeds.
ولكن في الحقيقة فإن هذه المجرات تتحرك بسرعة هائلة جدا.
They're moving around in this gravitational potential well of this cluster, OK.
إنها تدور بسبب نطاق جاذبية ذلك التجمع الهائل ، حسنا.
So all of these galaxies are moving.
إذاً كل هذه المجرات تتحرك.
We can measure the speeds of these galaxies, their orbital velocities,
وبإمكاننا قياس سرعة المجرات ، السرعة المدارية ،
and figure out how much mass is in this cluster.
وبالتالي معرفة كمية الكتلة التي في هذا التجمع.
And again, what we find is that there is much more mass there
ومرة أخرى ، نجد أن هناك كمية من الكتلة أكبر بكثير
than can be accounted for by the galaxies that we see.
من مجموع الكتلة للمجرات التي نراها.
Or if we look in other parts of the electromagnetic spectrum,
أو إذا نظرنا إلى أجزاء أخرى من الطيف الكهرومغناطيسي ،
we see that there's a lot of gas in this cluster, as well.
نلاحظ وجود الكثير من الغاز في هذا التجمع ،
But that cannot account for the mass either.
ولكن ذلك لا يفسر كمية الكتلة الموجودة أيضا.
In fact, there appears to be about ten times as much mass here
في الحقيقة ، هناك عشرة أضعاف الكتلة
in the form of this invisible or dark matter
على شكل مادة غير مرئية ، أو مادة مظلمة
as there is in the ordinary matter, OK.
من المادة الطبيعية ، حسنا.
It would be nice if we could see this dark matter a little bit more directly.
سيكون من الأفضل لو أننا استطعنا رؤية تلك المادة مباشرة.
I'm just putting this big, blue blob on there, OK,
حيث أنني أرمز لها بتلك الفقاعة الزرقاء الكبيرة ، حسنا ،
to try to remind you that it's there.
لأحاول تذكيركم بوجودها هناك.
Can we see it more visually? Yes, we can.
هل بالإمكان رؤيتها بالعين ؟ نعم ، نستطيع ذلك.
And so let me lead you through how we can do this.
سأريكم الان كيف بإمكاننا رؤيتها.
So here's an observer:
إذا كان هناك مراقب:
it could be an eye; it could be a telescope.
قد تكون عين مجردة أو منظار فلكي.
And suppose there's a galaxy out here in the universe.
ولنفترض أن هناك مجرة ما في الكون.
How do we see that galaxy?
كيف سنرى المجرة ؟
A ray of light leaves the galaxy and travels through the universe
سينطلق شعاع من الضوء من المجرة ويسافر عبر الكون
for perhaps billions of years
ربما لمليارات من السنين
before it enters the telescope or your eye.
قبل أن يصل إلى المنظار الفلكي أو العين.
Now, how do we deduce where the galaxy is?
الان ، كيف سنستدل على موقع المجرة ؟
Well, we deduce it by the direction that the ray is traveling
حسنا ، نستدل على ذلك عن طريق اتجاه الشعاع الضوئي
as it enters our eye, right?
عندما يصل إلى أعيننا ، أليس كذلك ؟
We say, the ray of light came this way;
لذلك نقول ، أن شعاع الضوء قادم من هذا الإتجاه ؛
the galaxy must be there, OK.
يجب أن تكون المجرة هناك ، حسنا.
Now, suppose I put in the middle a cluster of galaxies --
لنفترض الان أنني وضعت تجمعا من المجرات في الوسط --
and don't forget the dark matter, OK.
ولا تنسوا المادة المظلمة ، حسنا.
Now, if we consider a different ray of light, one going off like this,
والان ، إذا افترضنا أشعة مختلفة من الضوء ، أحدها يتجه بهذا الإتجاه ،
we now need to take into account
والان علينا أن نأخذ بالحسبان
what Einstein predicted when he developed general relativity.
ما توقعه أينشتاين عندما طور النظرية النسبية العامة.
And that was that the gravitational field, due to mass,
وهي أن مجال الجاذبية ، وبسبب الكتلة ،
will deflect not only the trajectory of particles,
يسبب انحرافا ليس في مسار الجسيمات فقط ،
but will deflect light itself.
بل في مسار الضوء أيضا.
So this light ray will not continue in a straight line,
لذلك فإن شعاع الضوء هذا لن يستمر في مسار مستقيم ،
but would rather bend and could end up going into our eye.
ولكن سينحني ومن ثم يصل إلى أعيننا.
Where will this observer see the galaxy?
ولكن أين سيتوقع المراقب مكان المجرة ؟
You can respond. Up, right?
بإمكانكم الإجابة. بالأعلى أليس كذلك ؟
We extrapolate backwards and say the galaxy is up here.
سنقوم بالتقدير بأن المجرة هناك في الأعلى.
Is there any other ray of light
هل هناك أي شعاع اخر من الضوء
that could make into the observer's eye from that galaxy?
من الممكن أن يصل من المجرة إلى عين المراقب ؟
Yes, great. I see people going down like this.
نعم ، عظيم. أرى البعض يشير إلى هناك بالأسفل.
So a ray of light could go down, be bent
إذا شعاع اخر من الضوء قد يتجه إلى الأسفل ، وسينحني
up into the observer's eye,
حتى يصل إلى عين المراقب ،
and the observer sees a ray of light here.
وسيرى المراقب شعاعا من الضوء هنا.
Now, take into account the fact that we live in
والان وبالأخذ بالإعتبار أننا نعيش في
a three-dimensional universe, OK,
كون ثلالثي الأبعاد ، حسنا ،
a three-dimensional space.
فضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد.
Are there any other rays of light that could make it into the eye?
هل هناك أي أشعة ضوء أخرى قد تصل إلى عين المراقب ؟
Yes! The rays would lie on a -- I'd like to see -- yeah, on a cone.
نعم ! الأشعة ستكون على شكل -- أحب أن أرى ذلك -- مخروط منطلق من المجرة.
So there's a whole ray of light -- rays of light on a cone --
إذا هناك مجموعة من الأشعة الضوئية -- أشعة ضوئية على شكل مخروط --
that will all be bent by that cluster
والتي ستنحني بسبب ذلك التجمع من المجرات
and make it into the observer's eye.
ومن ثم تصل إلى عين المراقب.
If there is a cone of light coming into my eye, what do I see?
وإذا كان هناك مخروطا من الأشعة الضوئية يصل إلى عيني ، فماذا يجب أن أرى ؟
A circle, a ring. It's called an Einstein ring. Einstein predicted that, OK.
دائرة ، حلقة. تدعى حلقة أينشتاين -- أينشتاين توقع ذلك ، حسنا.
Now, it will only be a perfect ring if the source, the deflector
والان ، ستكون حلقة مكتملة فقط إذا كان المصدر ، ومسبب الإنحناء ،
and the eyeball, in this case, are all in a perfectly straight line.
وكرة العين ، في هذه الحالة ، في خط مستقيم.
If they're slightly skewed, we'll see a different image.
وإذا كان هناك انحراف بسيط ، سنرى صورة مختلفة.
Now, you can do an experiment tonight over the reception, OK,
بإمكانكم الان القيام بتجربة هذا المساء في الردهة ، حسنا ،
to figure out what that image will look like.
لمعرفة كيف ستبدو الصورة.
Because it turns out that there is a kind of lens that we can devise,
لأنه تبين أن هناك نوع من العدسات من الممكن أن نوصي بها ،
that has the right shape to produce this kind of effect.
والتي لديها الشكل المناسب لإنتاج هذا النوع من الإنعكاس.
We call this gravitational lensing.
نسمي هذه عدسات الجاذبية.
And so, this is your instrument, OK.
إذا هذه هي معداتكم ، نعم.
(Laughter).
(ضحك)
But ignore the top part.
ولكن تجاهلوا الجزء الأعلى.
It's the base that I want you to concentrate, OK.
أريدكم أن تركزوا في القاعدة ، حسنا.
So, actually, at home, whenever we break a wineglass,
بالفعل ، في المنزل ، عندما نكسر كأس النبيذ ،
I save the bottom, take it over to the machine shop.
أحتفظ بالقاعدة ، ثم اخذها إلى الورشة.
We shave it off, and I have a little gravitational lens, OK.
ونقوم بتشذيبها ، فأكون قد حصلت على عدسة الجاذبية ، نعم.
So it's got the right shape to produce the lensing.
لديها الشكل المناسب للحصول على الإنعكاس المطلوب.
And so the next thing you need to do in your experiment
لذلك المطلوب عمله الان من أجل التجربة ،
is grab a napkin. I grabbed a piece of graph paper -- I'm a physicist. (Laughter)
الحصول على قماش منديل. استخدمت ورق الرسم البياني؛ لأنني فيزيائية. (ضحك)
So, a napkin. Draw a little model galaxy in the middle.
إذاً منديل. أرسم رسمة مصغرة للمجرة في الوسط.
And now put the lens over the galaxy,
والان دع العدسة فوق المجرة ،
and what you'll find is that you'll see a ring, an Einstein ring.
وستلاحظ أنك سترى حلقة ، حلقة أينشتاين.
Now, move the base off to the side,
والان حرك القاعدة جانبيا ،
and the ring will split up into arcs, OK.
وستنفصل الحلقة وتصبح على شكل قوس ، نعم.
And you can put it on top of any image.
وبإمكانكم تحريك العدسة فوق أي صورة.
On the graph paper, you can see
ففي ورق الرسم البياني ستلاحظون
how all the lines on the graph paper have been distorted.
كيف أن كل الخطوط البيانية قد انحرفت.
And again, this is a kind of an accurate model
ومرة أخرى ، هذا نموذج متطابق ودقيق
of what happens with the gravitational lensing.
لما يحدث في الإنعكاس بسبب الجاذبية.
OK, so the question is: do we see this in the sky?
حسنا ، السؤال الان هو : هل نرى ذلك بالفعل في الفضاء ؟
Do we see arcs in the sky when we look at, say, a cluster of galaxies?
هل نرى فعليا أقواس في الفضاء عندما ننظر ، لنقل ، إلى تجمع من المجرات ؟
And the answer is yes.
والإجابة هي : نعم.
And so, here's an image from the Hubble Space Telescope.
وهذه صورة من المنظار الفضائي هابل.
Many of the images you are seeing
والكثير من الصور التي ترونها
are earlier from the Hubble Space Telescope.
صور قديمة من المنظار الفضائي هابل.
Well, first of all, for the golden shape galaxies --
حسنا ، أولا ، بالنسبة للمجرات الذهبية اللون --
those are the galaxies in the cluster.
هذه هي المجرات التي في التجمع.
They're the ones that are embedded in that sea of dark matter
إنها المجرات التي تسبح في بحر من المادة المظلمة
that are causing the bending of the light
التي تسبب انحناء الضوء
to cause these optical illusions, or mirages, practically,
والذي بدوره يسبب الخدعة البصرية ، أو سرابا ، فعليا ،
of the background galaxies.
للمجرات التي في الخلف.
So the streaks that you see, all these streaks,
إذن الأشعة الضبابية التي ترونها ، كل تلك الأشعة ،
are actually distorted images of galaxies that are much further away.
هي بالفعل صورة مشوهة لمجرات بعيدة جدا.
So what we can do, then, is based on how much distortion
لذا ما نستطيع قياسه الان ، يعتمد على كمية التشوه الحاصل
we see in those images, we can calculate how much mass
في تلك الصور ، وبالتالي قياس كمية الكتلة
there must be in this cluster.
الموجودة في ذلك التجمع للمجرات.
And it's an enormous amount of mass.
وتلك كمية ضخمة جدا من الكتلة.
And also, you can tell by eye, by looking at this,
ويمكنكم أيضا ، بالعين المجردة ، وبالنظر إلى هذا ،
that these arcs are not centered on individual galaxies.
أن تلاحظوا أن هذه الأقواس ليست مركزة في مجرات بعينها؛
They are centered on some more spread out structure,
ولكن في تركيبة موزعة ومنتشرة.
and that is the dark matter
وتلك هي المادة المظلمة
in which the cluster is embedded, OK.
التي تحتوي ذلك التجمع من المجرات ، حسنا.
So this is the closest you can get to kind of seeing
هذه أفضل صورة لمشاهدة تلك المادة المظلمة
at least the effects of the dark matter with your naked eye.
على الأقل لمشاهدة التأثير الذي تحدثه تلك المادة المظلمة.
OK, so, a quick review then, to see that you're following.
مراجعة سريعة الان ، للتأكد من إلمامكم بالموضوع.
So the evidence that we have
إذاً الدليل الذي لدينا على أن
that a quarter of the universe is dark matter --
ربع الكون عبارة عن مادة مظلمة --
this gravitationally attracting stuff --
تلك الجاذبية الهائلة --
is that galaxies, the speed with which stars orbiting galaxies
هي أن المجرات ، والسرعة التي تدور بها النجوم فيها
is much too large; it must be embedded in dark matter.
كبيرة جدا؛ لدرجة أنه لابد أن تكون محاطة بمادة مظلمة.
The speed with which galaxies within clusters are orbiting is much too large;
والسرعة التي تدور بها أيضا المجرات في داخل التجمعات هائلة جدا؛
it must be embedded in dark matter.
لدرجة أنها لابد أن تكون أيضا محاطة بمادة مظلمة.
And we see these gravitational lensing effects, these distortions
ونستطيع أن نرى تأثير الإنعكاس بسبب الجاذبية ، وذلك التشويه في الصورة
that say that, again, clusters are embedded in dark matter.
وذلك يؤدي أيضا إلى أن التجمعات كذلك لابد أن تحاط بمادة مظلمة.
OK. So now, let's turn to dark energy.
حسنا. الان لننتقل إلى الطاقة المظلمة.
So to understand the evidence for dark energy, we need to discuss something
لفهم الأدلة على وجود الطاقة المظلمة ، علينا مناقشة شئ ما
that Stephen Hawking referred to in the previous session.
شرحه ستيفن هوكينج في المناقشة السابقة.
And that is the fact that space itself is expanding.
وهي حقيقة أن الفضاء نفسه في حالة تمدد.
So if we imagine a section of our infinite universe --
لذا فإذا تخيلنا قسما من الفضاء اللا متناهي ، حسنا ،
and so I've put down four spiral galaxies, OK --
ووضعنا فيه أربعة مجرات حلزونية ، حسنا.
and imagine that you put down a set of tape measures,
ولو تخيلنا وجود خطوط لقياس المسافات ،
so every line on here corresponds to a tape measure,
لذا فإن كل خط هنا يمثل مقياسا --
horizontal or vertical, for measuring where things are.
أفقيا أو عموديا -- لتحديد أماكن الأجسام.
If you could do this, what you would find
إذا استطعنا من فعل ذلك ، فإننا سنجد
that with each passing day, each passing year,
أننا مع كل يوم يمر ، وكل سنة تمر ،
each passing billions of years, OK,
وبعد مرور مليارات من السنين ، حسنا ،
the distance between galaxies is getting greater.
المسافة بين المجرات ستزداد.
And it's not because galaxies are moving
وليس ذلك بسبب تحرك المجرات
away from each other through space.
متباعدة عن بعضها في الفضاء
They're not necessarily moving through space.
بل إنها قد لا تتحرك في الفضاء.
They're moving away from each other
لكنها تتباعد عن بعضها
because space itself is getting bigger, OK.
بسبب تمدد الفضاء نفسه ، حسنا.
That's what the expansion of the universe or space means.
وهذا هو معنى تمدد أو توسع الكون.
So they're moving further apart.
لذلك فإن المجرات في تباعد دائم.
Now, what Stephen Hawking mentioned, as well,
والان ماذكره ستيفن هوكينج ، أيضا ،
is that after the Big Bang, space expanded at a very rapid rate.
أنه بعد الإنفجار العظيم ، تمدد الفضاء بمعدل عالي جدا.
But because gravitationally attracting matter
ولكن بسبب قوى الجاذبية للمادة
is embedded in this space,
التي تملأ هذا الفضاء ،
it tends to slow down the expansion of the space, OK.
فإنها تسبب في إبطاء حركة تمدد الفضاء .
So the expansion slows down with time.
لذا فإن التمدد يتباطأ مع مرور الزمن.
So, in the last century, OK, people debated
ففي القرن الأخير ، اختلف العلماء
about whether this expansion of space would continue forever;
عما إذا كان هذا التمدد في الفضاء سيستمر للأبد ،
whether it would slow down, you know,
أو أنه سيتباطأ ، كما تعرفون ،
will be slowing down, but continue forever;
سيتباطأ ، ولكن يستمر إلى الأبد.
slow down and stop, asymptotically stop;
أو أنه سيتباطأ ومن ثم يتوقف ، أو يتجه نحو التوقف ،
or slow down, stop, and then reverse, so it starts to contract again.
أو أنه سيتباطأ ، ثم يقف ، ثم يعكس الإتجاه ، ويبدأ بالإنكماش مرة أخرى.
So a little over a decade ago,
لذا قبل نحو أكثر من عشر سنوات بقليل ،
two groups of physicists and astronomers
قامت مجموعة من الفيزيائيين وعلماء الفلك
set out to measure the rate at which
بدراسة معدل التباطؤ
the expansion of space was slowing down, OK.
في سرعة تمدد الفضاء .
By how much less is it expanding today,
أو ماهو معدل التباطؤ في التمدد الحاصل اليوم
compared to, say, a couple of billion years ago?
مقارنة ، لنقل ، بمعدل التباطؤ قبل بضع مليارات من السنين ؟
The startling answer to this question, OK, from these experiments,
الإجابة المروعة لهذا السؤال ، نعم ، من تلك التجارب ،
was that space is expanding at a faster rate today
هي أن الفضاء في معدل تمدد أكبر اليوم ،
than it was a few billion years ago, OK.
من قبل بضع مليارات من السنين .
So the expansion of space is actually speeding up.
لذا فإن الحقيقة هي أن الفضاء في تمدد بسرعة أكبر.
This was a completely surprising result.
وهذه كانت مفاجأة كبرى.
There is no persuasive theoretical argument for why this should happen, OK.
لم يكن هناك من نظرية أو فرضية مقنعة لتفسير ذلك ، حسنا.
No one was predicting ahead of time this is what's going to be found.
ولم يكن أحد ليتوقع تلك النتيجة.
It was the opposite of what was expected.
بل كانت عكس كل التوقعات.
So we need something to be able to explain that.
لذلك فنحن بحاجة إلى شيء يفسر كل ذلك.
Now it turns out, in the mathematics,
والان تبين ، بالمسائل الرياضية ،
you can put it in as a term that's an energy,
أنه بإمكاننا حسابها كمتغير للطاقة.
but it's a completely different type of energy
ولكنها نوع مختلف جدا من الطاقة
from anything we've ever seen before.
بل عن أي شيء رأيناه من قبل.
We call it dark energy,
نسميها الطاقة المظلمة ،
and it has this effect of causing space to expand.
ولديها ذلك التأثير المسبب لتمدد الفضاء.
But we don't have a good motivation
ولكن ليس لدينا سبب جيد
for putting it in there at this point, OK.
لوضعها هناك في هذه اللحظة ، نعم.
So it's really unexplained as to why we need to put it in.
إذ أنه ليس لدينا تفسير مقنع لوضعها هناك.
Now, so at this point, then, what I want to really emphasize to you,
الان ، في هذه المرحلة ، أريد التأكيد لكم
is that, first of all, dark matter and dark energy
أولا ، أن المادة المظلمة والطاقة المظلمة
are completely different things, OK.
شيئان مختلفان تماما ، نعم.
There are really two mysteries out there as to what makes up most of the universe,
هناك بالفعل لغزين بخصوص المواد التي يتكون منها الكون ،
and they have very different effects.
ولكل منهما تأثير مختلف جدا.
Dark matter, because it gravitationally attracts,
المادة المظلمة ، بسبب تأثير قواها الجاذبية
it tends to encourage the growth of structure, OK.
فهي تساعد على بناء التجمعات ، حسنا.
So clusters of galaxies will tend to form,
لذلك فإنها تساعد على بناء تجمعات للمجرات ،
because of all this gravitational attraction.
بسبب كل تلك القوى من الجاذبية.
Dark energy, on the other hand,
أما الطاقة المظلمة ، من جهة أخرى ،
is putting more and more space between the galaxies,
فهي تسبب في خلق الكثير من المساحات بين المجرات.
makes it, the gravitational attraction between them decrease,
وبالتالي تجعل -- قوى التجاذب بينها -- أقل ،
and so it impedes the growth of structure.
ولذلك فهي تقاوم بناء التجمعات.
So by looking at things like clusters of galaxies,
إذا عندما ننظر إلى تجمعات المجرات ،
and how they -- their number density,
وكيف أن -- كثافتها العددية ،
how many there are as a function of time --
ونسبة ازدياد الكثافة مع مرور الوقت --
we can learn about how dark matter and dark energy
نستطيع معرفة كيف أن المادة المظلمة والطاقة المظلمة
compete against each other in structure forming.
يتنافسون فيما بينهم في تكوين بنية التجمعات المجرية.
In terms of dark matter, I said that we don't have any,
وبالمقارنة مع المادة المظلمة ، قلت لكم أنه ليس لدينا ،
you know, really persuasive argument for dark energy.
كما تعرفون ، أي فرضية مقنعة بالنسبة للطاقة المظلمة.
Do we have anything for dark matter? And the answer is yes.
ولكن هل لدينا فرضية مقنعة للمادة المظلمة ؟ والإجابة هي : نعم.
We have well-motivated candidates for the dark matter.
لدينا مرشح "مدعوم" للمادة المظلمة.
Now, what do I mean by well motivated?
والان ، ماذا أعني عندما أقول "مدعوم" ؟
I mean that we have mathematically consistent theories
أعني أننا نملك نظريات رياضية متسقة
that were actually introduced
والتي كانت في الحقيقة
to explain a completely different phenomenon, OK,
لتفسير ظواهر مختلفة جدا ،
things that I haven't even talked about,
أشياء لم أتحدث عنها أصلا ،
that each predict the existence
ولكنها جميعا تتوقع وجود
of a very weakly interacting, new particle.
مادة جديدة ولا تترك أثرا.
So, this is exactly what you want in physics:
وهذا مانبحث عنه بالضبط في الفيزياء:
where a prediction comes out of a mathematically consistent theory
عندما تأتي توقعات من نظرية رياضية متماسكة
that was actually developed for something else.
والتي طورت في الأصل لشيء مختلف جدا.
But we don't know if either of those
ولكننا لا نعلم حتى الان ما إذا كانت تلك
are actually the dark matter candidate, OK.
هي فعليا المادة المظلمة المرشحة.
One or both, who knows? Or it could be something completely different.
أحدهما أو كلاهما ، من يعرف ؟ وقد تكون شيئا مختلفا كليا.
Now, we look for these dark matter particles
الان ، نحن نبحث عن جسيمات تلك المادة المظلمة
because, after all, they are here in the room, OK,
لأنها في النهاية ، متواجدة هنا في القاعة ، نعم ،
and they didn't come in the door.
وهي لم تدخل عبر الباب.
They just pass through anything.
لأنها تعبر من خلال الأشياء.
They can come through the building, through the Earth --
بإمكانها العبور من خلال المبنى ، من خلال الكرة الأرضية؛
they're so non-interacting.
ليس لها أي أثر.
So one way to look for them is to build detectors
لذلك فإن إحدى الطرق للبحث عنها هي عبر بناء جهاز كاشف
that are extremely sensitive to a dark matter particle coming through and bumping it.
حساس جدا لجسيمات المادة المظلمة العابرة ويصطدم بها
So a crystal that will ring if that happens.
و ستدق البلورة حينها إذا حدث ذلك.
So one of my colleagues up the road and his collaborators
لذلك فإن أحد زملائي القريبين وبعض من المتعاونين معه
have built such a detector.
بنوا ذلك الجهاز.
And they've put it deep down in an iron mine in Minnesota,
ووضعوه عميقا في الأسفل في منجم حديدي في مينيسوتا ،
OK, deep under the ground, and in fact, in the last couple of days
حسنا ؟ -- عميقا جدا تحت الأرض -- في الحقيقة ، في اليومين الأخيرين
announced the most sensitive results so far.
أعلنوا أكثر النتائج أهمية حتى الان.
They haven't seen anything, OK, but it puts limits on what the mass
لم يروا شيئا ، نعم ، ولكنها بينت حدود كمية الكتلة
and the interaction strength of these dark matter particles are.
و مقياس تفاعل جسيمات تلك المادة المظلمة.
There's going to be a satellite telescope launched later this year
وسيكون هناك منظار فلكي فضائي لاحقا هذه السنة.
and it will look towards the middle of the galaxy,
وسيتم توجيهه باتجاه وسط المجرة ،
to see if we can see dark matter particles annihilating
لمعرفة ما إذا كانت جسيمات المادة المظلمة ستخفي
and producing gamma rays that could be detected with this.
أو تنتج أشعة جاما والتي من الممكن كشفها بواسطة ذلك المنظار.
The Large Hadron Collider, a particle physics accelerator,
ومسارع الجسيمات الفيزيائية LHC ،
that we'll be turning on later this year.
والذي سيعمل لاحقا في هذه السنة.
It is possible that dark matter particles might be produced
من المحتمل أن ينتج جسيمات المادة المظلمة
at the Large Hadron Collider.
بداخل المسارع.
Now, because they are so non-interactive,
ولكن لأن تلك الجسيمات لا تترك أثرا ،
they will actually escape the detector,
فإنه لا يمكن كشفها ،
so their signature will be missing energy, OK.
ولكن الدليل على وجودها سيكون فقدان بعض من الطاقة ، حسنا.
Now, unfortunately, there is a lot of new physics
والان ولسوء الحظ ، فهناك الكثير من الأسباب الفيزيائية
whose signature could be missing energy,
التي تسبب فقدان جزء من الطاقة ،
so it will be hard to tell the difference.
وسيكون من الصعب تحديد الفرق.
And finally, for future endeavors, there are telescopes being designed
وأخيرا ، وللمحاولات المستقبلية ، يتم تصميم منظار خاص
specifically to address the questions of dark matter and dark energy --
للإجابة على الأسئلة عن المادة المظلمة والطاقة المظلمة:
ground-based telescopes, and there are three space-based telescopes
منظار فلكي أرضي. وهناك ثلاثة مناظير فلكية فضائية
that are in competition right now
والتي تتنافس فيما بينها الان
to be launched to investigate dark matter and dark energy.
للإنطلاق إلى الفضاء لدراسة المادة المظلمة والطاقة المظلمة.
So in terms of the big questions:
لذا فالأسئلة المهمة هي :
what is dark matter? What is dark energy?
ماهي المادة المظلمة ؟ وماهي الطاقة المظلمة ؟
The big questions facing physics.
وهي الأسئلة الأهم التي تواجه علم الفيزياء.
And I'm sure you have lots of questions,
وإنني متأكدة تماما أنكم تملكون الان الكثير من الأسئلة.
which I very much look forward to addressing
والتي أتطلع للإجابة عليها
over the next 72 hours, while I'm here. Thank you.
خلال الـ 72 ساعة القادمة أثناء تواجدي هنا ، نعم. شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)